<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendious declaration of the excellent uertues of a certain lateli inuentid oile, callid for the uuorthines thereof oile imperial VVith the maner hou the same is to be usid, to the benefite of mankind, against innumerable diseasis. Vuriten by Thomas Rainold Doc. of Phisick.</title>
            <title>Epistola, rationem modumque propinandi radicis chynae decocti pertractans. English</title>
            <author>Vesalius, Andreas, 1514-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850866</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10504)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 350:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendious declaration of the excellent uertues of a certain lateli inuentid oile, callid for the uuorthines thereof oile imperial VVith the maner hou the same is to be usid, to the benefite of mankind, against innumerable diseasis. Vuriten by Thomas Rainold Doc. of Phisick.</title>
                  <title>Epistola, rationem modumque propinandi radicis chynae decocti pertractans. English</title>
                  <author>Vesalius, Andreas, 1514-1564.</author>
                  <author>Raynalde, Thomas, fl. 1540-1551.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Ioan. Gryphius excudebat,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Venetiis :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDLI. [1551]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In fact a translation by Raynalde of: Vesalius, Andreas. Epistola, rationem modumque propinandi radicis chynae decocti pertractans.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:1"/>
            <p>A COMPENDIOVS <hi>DECLARATION OF THE</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uertues of a certain lateli inuentid oile, callid for the uuorthines thereof Oile Imperial.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVITH THE MANER HOV THE</hi> ſame is to be uſid, to the benefite of Mankind, against Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable diſeaſis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vuriten by Thomas Rainold Doc. of Phiſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>VIRTVTE DVCE COMITE FORTVNA.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>VENETITS</hi> Ioan. Gryphius excudebat. MDLI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO HIS SINGVLAR</hi> frind Francis Mery marchant of the Cite of London Thomas Rainold uuiſshith, al helth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> ſtrong obligation uuherein, throu your ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial humanite, y find mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf right ſtraightli obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid and bound, uuil in no uuiſe ſuffer forgetfulnes of the infinite benefites daili receauid at your hands in to mi mindful mind to make eni unlau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful entree. But continualli calling on, &amp; ſetting before mine inuuard eyes, on thone ſide, the uuaighti burden of bound dueti, on thouther, the feoble correſpondencie of mi ſmal poure, engendrith in mi fantaſi ſo perplex and douteful deliberation, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring the remiſsnes of mi slender poure, uuith the exceſs of your ſingular meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, y can conceaue but ſmal hope uuith ſo litil force, euer to diſcarge me of ſo greate and graue a bond. Notuuithſtanding, uuilling in this behalf to enſue the example of honest dettars, as ye, <hi>I</hi> am certain, do of ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Creditors, uuhereas y am not able at one paiment, to aquite the total ſum of mi due det, if as pour, time, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and occation do geue, y declare mi ſelf, in that y mai, ſumuuhat touuards, and readili uuilling, y dout not but your uuont curteſi uuil accept dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t endeuar, in place
<pb facs="tcp:16101:3"/>of a meane contentation. Vuhereas a feu moneths paſsid, ye bought, onli oppon mi commendation, a certain por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Oile, ſurnamid Imperial, thereoppon requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me to uurite you a short memori of the most nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualitees thereof, ſo ſoone as conuenient leaſar uuold ſuffer me, parteli to perfurm mi promes to the inuentor of the ſaid Oile longſith made, but cheifli glad to embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce this occation, uuherebi y mought ſeeme to haue found ſum matter, therein to shou the inclination of mi hart touuards the accompliſsheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of eni your uertuous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, y fourthuuith toke in hand to compile, as ye ſee, this ſimple and rude treatiſe. The uuhiche, albeit it shal mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festli appere far &amp; uuide diſanſuuerable, bothe to your expectation, mi deſire, and alſo the uuoorthines of the matter, yet y truſt ye uuil haue reſpect rather to the prompt good uuil of one, uuhiche in eueri thing to his utter, is muche fainar to gratifie, then hable, to ſatisfie ſuche his rare &amp; approuid frind. And in your ſo doing, ye shal encreaſe in me ſprite and courage, by litil and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til, to excogitate hereaffter ſum matter more peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aggreable bothe to your appetite, and alſo mi fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſi. In the meane uuhile, fare ye moſt harteli uuel. From Venice the firſt of Marche.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ONOR, ſaith the good old pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerb, nouriſshith art: whiche ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of no leſs uerite, then antiquite, if in oure aege as in times auncient were remembrid and regardid, no doute but, th' actiuite of mens witts at this preſent being no leſs liueli, and forward then, the ſame of them in times paſsid, there wold be brought furth in theſe our daies, as gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate effects of wittie ingene, as haue ben from time to time from our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prediceſſars ſucceſsiueli hitherto receauid: who hathe ſo litill wordli experience that loking abrode ſeith not with his eyes, withi thes feu yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, in al kind of arts and ſciences ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che an increaſe, yea perfection engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid &amp; upſprung, that almoſt it ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith there can be no addition made to
<pb facs="tcp:16101:4"/>that the late wits of men haue contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, inuentid, and throuhli furniſshid? So that the fine induſtrie and sharp wittines of men in thoſe latter daies in al maner of knouledge, &amp; experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, haue ſo far and earneſtli trauelid, and eache his ſcience ſo renuid, &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſshid, that the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t effects and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, of thes feu yeares, mai be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parid, and eſtemid equiualent with the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of mani hundrith yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res before. Examples hereof be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni &amp; plentitul, that were it to mi pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pourpoſe, y mought therewith furniſshe furth a greate uolume. But as there be diuers, whome the ſight and fruition of faire fruicts do muche delight and reioice, ſo be there wel few, whome the care to ſet, or chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſshe the plats wherefro ſuche fruits mought be lookid for, doith enithing touche, wherebi it cummith to paſs, that mani of whome outherwiſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught
<pb facs="tcp:16101:4"/>be hoopid greate aboundance of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fruits and uertuous inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, eather for lack of ſufficient ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kor, as the ueri humor of there tree, thei can not encreaſe, ne til due ſeaſon nouriſhe there fruit, but are conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnid to ſuffer them periſshe in the bloſſome, or if there good aduenture be, to attaigne unto the perfection of fruit, the ſame, with the blaſts of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie is ſo windshaken, that the tree of his fruit litil praiſe &amp; leſs proffet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioieth. That foule uice of ingratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, right mani apt &amp; hable witts, from the atcheauing &amp; entrepriſe of mani wurthie matters, doith daili, no doute, withold &amp; greateli diſcourage, hauing ouer muche regard &amp; reſpect, tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards the uilite of that comon raigning deuilliſshe uice. But in there ſo doing, as peraduenture thei mai be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did for wiſe, circumſpect, &amp; maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnars of thereoune tranquillite and
<pb facs="tcp:16101:5"/>quietnes, ſo yet ſuche priuate pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie is open iniurie &amp; enimite to the common welth of mankind and al poſterite. Yf oure auncients wold haue ben abaſshid, or witholden fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel doing, or writing, for eni ſuche reſpects, raigning in there dais as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ingratitude as nou in ours, we shold haue found ourſelf at this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, in ſo profound darcknes &amp; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie of al uerite, that litill shold be the difference betuuene us and bruit beeſts.</p>
            <p>Treu it is, that to the ſaid incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modite of Enuie be ſubiectid, in maner with oute exception, al ſuche, who with there pen, paine themſelf to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſshe eni kind of matter, nameli being annexid with ſum noueltie or rarenes. For anon as in writing aman haue his concepts once diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid, &amp; ſet at large, ful mani Iudges, &amp; of as uariable ſenſes &amp; opinions doith
<pb facs="tcp:16101:5"/>that pout writing furthuuith acquire; Sum wil improue it becauſe nothing can like them but there oune: Sum, be cauſe thei not wel underſtand the matter: Outher, to ſeeme therebi the wiſar and more skillful: But he that is ſo tender ouer his name that to shun and auoid the nipps of girning Enuie, wil abſtaign and forbare to puttfurth eni ſuche tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whereuuith the geuer of al goodnes doith endue him, take he heade, leeſt whilſt he ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kith by that meanes to ſeme wordli wiſe, he becum ungodli wickid: For ſomuche as it ought to be perſuua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did to al unfainid Chriſtians, no man to be wiſe, to be cunning, mightie, ritche, of eni outher gifft at gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue receauid, for his oune oneli peculiar aduauntage, glori, promotion, welth, or pleaſir, but thereuuithal to the utilite, commodite, &amp; benefit of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that mai lie in him: And where
<pb facs="tcp:16101:6"/>as ther be mani and mani things, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof the brittel and feoble nature of mankind hath daili neceſsite, &amp; indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as wel to the ſaffe maintaining and upholding of his helth &amp; wel fare, as alſo to the repairing &amp; reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſame being enithing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied or emperiſshid, who ſo can deuiſe or inuent eni maner of thing whereby man mai perceauer, and the better continue in good helth, or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len therefro, the ſonar and moore ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuousli recouer the ſame: Suche inuentor and deuiſar in mi opinion, not onli meritith praiſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of al them that wourtheli be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendid under the name of man, but alſo in conſcience is ſtraightli bound, to publiſshe it ſo largeli, that the utilite thereof mai be extendid &amp; ſpred ouer al men: For therefore, no doute doith god enſpire diuers men with ſundri knouledge, that eache
<pb facs="tcp:16101:6"/>with outher frindeli communicating his receauid talent, one therebi shold find himſelf the nearar bound &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to the outher.</p>
            <p>So that by ſuche unpartial diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of his manifold graces, god hath throu his diuine pollici, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain amite, &amp; leege, meruelousli unitid and knit al this wide wordle to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Vvere it not, that one man, one Cite, one Nation, had neade of an ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditees, wiſedome, counceil, help, ſerueis, ſoukar, ritches, uerili one wold contemn &amp; neglect an outher wurs then ſtraunge doggs togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Conſiderid then, that gods bountie doith thus gather and bind us in one, throu his indifferent liberalise, who that enuieth, diſpraiſith, detractith an outhers gifft, malignith, deſpicith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouith, and doith open contumeli euen to god the geuer thereof. Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:16101:7"/>forcith it houſmal in apparence ſuche qualite do ſeame: forſomuche as al &amp; ſum, the leſs withe the moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, at his hands ought to be taken with like tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckfullnes: neather is eni thing to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as litil or ſmaul, that from ſo plentiful an hand procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith: But what shold y ſpeake of the ſmalnes or greatenes of eni qualite, when al that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtith in the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mans light hed: Vve ſee daili certain arts and qualitees, had in the top of al eſtimation, there Artificers embracid, honorid, &amp; enritchid, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che notuuithſtanding ſolitil proffite the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mone welthe of men, that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che rather thereto thei be mere perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious &amp; dammageable: wurthie, if oure Iudgement, throu blind appetite were not wholi corruptid, to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotton, unexerſicid &amp; utterli baniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shid: wheras in the meane white ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni innocentarts, auaileable toal men,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:7"/>neceſſari, godli, uertuous, eather lie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together neglectid, &amp; uneſteamid, not able to miniſtre unto there poure practiſars a ſcarce liuing, orels be ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri slenderli regardid &amp; ſcantli lookid on: So that as it is offt and trueli ſaid, eueri thing as it is taken, and not as it is in de de.</p>
            <p>But as we ſee that great heaps be compilid of mani ſmaul handfulls, if eueri man for this part, ſetting aſide diſdaign at outhers uertue, wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in al his life to contriue or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent one oneli feate in eni what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſcience conducible to mankind, it is eaſie to be underſtandid to what encreaſe &amp; abſolutenes within feu yeares al maner of ſciences mought attaigne: And to approoche ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuhat neare to mi prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did pourpoſe, In the noble ſcience of Phiſick, as it can not be denied, but that the clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cks of times paſsid profeſsing the
<pb facs="tcp:16101:8"/>ſame, haue uniuerſalli in eueri part thereof, ſo earneſtli and fruitfulli tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelid, that great wunder, &amp; theruuith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al exceading pleaſer it is to behold the curiouſe and ingeniouſe induſtrie of them. One deſcanting oppon a nother, to inueſtigate and right oute enithing miſtaken or miſtought by there prediceſſors: to explicate and cleare thigs obſcureli &amp; darkli by ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eather throu breuite, orels rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, entreatid of before: to Compoſe and deuiſe medicines of moſt effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie againſt al maner of Maladies infeſting the weake bodi of man: briefli to ſtable and reduce that wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſcience, ſo neare as the debilite of mans brains could approoche, unto Suche exactnes, that of a diuining &amp; geſsing nouledge it mought becum a certain &amp; unfallible ſcience. Euenſo as wel, it can not be trueli denied, but that in this oure time god hath ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridup
<pb facs="tcp:16101:8"/>excellent uertuous witts whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſo ſtraitli cal to examination al the doctrine and docume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts lefft from the auncients, waieng, &amp; ſo aduiſidli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trieng, the ſincere from the contrarie, that if thei procead as thei haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, it is like within feu yeares, that ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wil be ſo renuid, refreſshid, and purgid, that thei whiche hitherto haue boren al the bruit, &amp; haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainid al autorite, wil leeſe a greate portion of there creadit, &amp; be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid rather for good meaners, then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite true teachars.</p>
            <p>This diligens not alone in the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatiue parts of Phiſick is uſid, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the pradiue, daili being inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid, more effectuous, more ſicure, and more expedite remedies againſt diuers tedious, dangerous, and hard curable diſeaſes? Hou mani faire Simples are nou in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mone uſe, whiche to oure forefathers were utterli unknouuen
<pb facs="tcp:16101:9"/>&amp; unſeene: As Reubarb, Sene, Gaſsia ſiſtula, Manna, Sugre, Ambte, Muſk, Ciuet, Camphire, Turbith, the herbs Angelica, imperialis, with a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of outher ſimples of excellent graces &amp; qualitees: whiche if thei lackid, the fairiſt floures of Phiſitions garlants were gon withal: Again, by the art of diſtillation, (unto the auncients ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terli unknouuen) hou mani faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Baumes, oiles, and outher ſuche things haue there ben of late daies contriuid, whiche to the paurpoſes whereto thei were inuentid be of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che forſe &amp; efficacie, ſum againſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuard diſeaſes and ſum againſt the inuuard that no outher Simple or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt medicines, in times paſsid diuiſid mai be to them in eni wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parid. For by the feate of deſtillation the purar parts and ſtrength being befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re biried or drounid in the groſs ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terialnes of the herbs, Rootes, gums,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:9"/>ſeedes, wuds, fruittes or outher what ſoeuer ſimples be artificialli diuidid, &amp; extractid in ſuche wiſe, that the water, Oile, or liqeur, affter that ſort throu expert handling ſublimid &amp; diſtillid, in manifold wiſe ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith the ſimple wherefro it is ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid, whether ye regard the more cele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite in wurking, or els the greater effi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacie in operation.</p>
            <p>Vvhat water, Decoctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the beſt of wines, can ſo ſpeadeli confort and reuiue a parſon for weekenes of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes hauing the hart faile, as the liqueur callid quinteſſence, whiche is nothing els but aqua vitae, or aquacompoſita,<note place="margin">The uertu of quinteſſence.</note> by extreme diſtillation deliuerid from al wateriſſhenes, reſting onli a pure and exceading ſubtile eſſence, whiche can Iuſteli be namid neatherſire, Aer, water, nor Earth: and therefore is taken to be as il were of a ſifft being or eſſence, different in nature from the
<pb facs="tcp:16101:10"/>eſſence, being, or qualite of the .iiii. Elements: The ſame alſo againſt late ſurfetts enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drid, eather throu natiue slacknes, and cold complexion of the ſtomack, orels by the euel qualite or ouermouche quantite of meate, hou mutche it preuailith, daili experience plainli declarith: And what outher liqeur ſo ſoone as it receauith impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and vertue of eni thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a while ſteepid therein, and the ſame vertue ſo ſpeadili communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catith to the boodi that receauith it outeuuards ouer inuuards as cauſe mai require?</p>
            <p>Vvhat vſual oile, ſo ſuuifftli pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netratith, or entrith into the ſkin,<note place="margin">The poure of Oleum philo ſophorum.</note> fleſshe, and depth of al parts of the bodie, as the oile namid oleum philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophorum: So valiantli doith diſsipat diſcuſs, diſparſe eni collection of cold knottie, and viſcous humors, in what part of the bodie ſo euer thei be
<pb facs="tcp:16101:10"/>found withoutfurth: ſo effectuouſli healith old aches &amp; pains: diſſoluing &amp; melting, the craſsenes &amp; groſsenes of gluy humors: warming, &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing parts throu diſtemperancie of cold debilitate: with outher infinite propretees.</p>
            <p>Here alſo, if y liſtid to be long, y mought make mention of the oiles of lignum Aloes, of Nutmeggs, of Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, Geniper, Sulphur, Eggs, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni outher things: Vvhiche as thei be ſingular againſt innumerable infirmities, ſo be thei, &amp; al that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto y haue reherſid, far and wide ſurmountid in al graces and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, of an oile, not mani yeares ſith,<note place="margin">The excellen cie of Oile Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perial.</note> bi a familiar frind of mine inuentid, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid for the wurthines thereof, Oile imperial. To this oile, al outher natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or artificial that thei be, vnto this dai contriuid or inuentid, be as far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors, as the courſenes of outher ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:16101:11"/>Mettalls to the purite and extreme fineſs of gold.</p>
            <p>But according as is ſaide before, as the maner of diſtillation of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and oiles, is a neuu and late inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the verie auncient phiſitions, vnheard of and vnknouue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this oile imperial, hathe ben as wel to the Neuu as to the old hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto vtterli, ſo far as y can yet ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, vnknouuen, outher then to mi ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de frind: Vvho, abought fiue yeares paſt, affter long labour, conſtant dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, &amp; his no ſmal charges emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that behalf, hauig at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght it to paſs: for the accuſtumid fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarite betuuene vs, geuig me a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain portion thereof, requirid, that y wold according to mi ſimple ſkil in phiſick, ſumuuhat enſtruct him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reto it mought appeare to be moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducible, and what bi reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y could iudge the cheif qualitees thereof
<pb facs="tcp:16101:11"/>ſhold be.</p>
            <p>Vvhen y had wel and aduiſedli conſiderid the ſingular grace of theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and receauid ſufficient informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the particulars, whereof it was compoſid, y geſsid anon, that it could not be, but that ſpecial and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table effects againſt a wordle of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, therebi dueli vſid, ſhold to mankind en ſue: Vvherefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his requeſt, ſo far as Art and reaſon had tought me, in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting y declarid, what commoditees were moſt likeli to be lokid for, bi it: And againſt what diſeaſes it ſeamid to be moſt auaileable: Notuuithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forſomuche as to iudge the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of eni medicine onli by art and reaſon, without a confirmation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendrid by experience, is not aluuai ſure, ne voide of parel: I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelid him not to be ouer bold, vntil ſuche time that by leaſer, as ſundrie occations
<pb facs="tcp:16101:12"/>ſhold offer themſelf, reaſon bi practiſe were eſtabliſshid.</p>
            <p>Sith whiche time in deade, bothe he and outher for there parts, and y for mine, not onli in Ingland, but alſo in diuers outher quartars beyand the ſeas hauing made ſufficient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uffs, of the vndoutid good qualites whereuuith aboundantli it is enduid And beſides that, being nueli again by the ſaide inuentor of this diuine oile, ſolliſitatid, with mi rudenes, to publiſshe vnto the wordle ſuche ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and veritable experience, as from time to time hath ben fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and tried by practice to be faithfulli true: y tho ught mi ſmal labor and paines to be emploied herein, to the ſatisfaction of mi frinds honeſt: demaund, and the vndouted vtilite whiche mought ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cede to al them, that driuen throu im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunite of ſuche like diſeaſes, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraignid to ſeake for ſpeadie and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurid
<pb facs="tcp:16101:12"/>reamedie, ſhold not deſerue eni diſcommendation, or enuious reproff of the Maleuolent, but rather the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable acceptation of vpright and honeſt iudgements.</p>
            <p>Plainlie yet confeſſing, that in mi ſelf y can not find ſo exact and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hablenes, ſo liueli to expreſſe the valeur of this excellent oile, as the wurthines thereof wold require, and mimind deſire? Onli y mai, and wil auaunt mi ſelf herein to vſe ſuche ſin cerire and ſinglenes of verite, that y truſt none ſhal haue eni iuſt occation to accuſe me of vanite, or eni priuate affection vſid in this behalf: as to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue extollid the dignite of the ſaide oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, eni thig aboue the merits, or aboue that, the effect thereof, bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, aright vſid; mai accordingli approue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme: And albeit the ſingular qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litees of it be greater, then mai in feu wurdes be comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did &amp; ſetfurth,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:13"/>yet minentent is not thereof to ſai al that mai be ſaide or writen, but onli by exemplifieng of ſum portion of his infinite vertues, to open the gate, wherebi the ſkilful and lernid, bi the feu experiences here reherſid mai en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre bi them ſellf into a brodar camp of farther knouledge.</p>
            <p>To thend alſo, that the veriſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of al that ſhalbe ſaid thereof mai to the lernid the moore cleareli ap peare, here wil y trueli reherſe the ſum of the particular ingredience whiche to the compoſition of this oile do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre: withoute yet opening al the circumſtance vſid abought the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it, leſt the autor thereof ſhold, not without a cauſe claime him ſelf iniuried &amp; wrongid therebi.<note place="margin">The ſimples uuhereof Oile Imperial is made.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the ſimples. Firſt, Cloues Mace, Nutmeggs, the rootes of Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wale, of Angelica, Imperialis, Enula ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana, Gentiana, &amp; Petaſites; the rinds
<pb facs="tcp:16101:13"/>and kernels of Citrons, Oranges, &amp; Lemmons: the wuds, of lignum Alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, lignum uitae, and lignum Aſphala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi: thes herbs dried, Origanum Cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenſe, Diptamus Creticus: Scordion Cretenſe: Squinantum: folium Indu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Rooſemary: Saueri: Mariorame: Herb Maudlene: the ſedes of Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, Ameos, Daucus, Baſel, Semen Santonicum: Coriander, and Carui.</p>
            <p>Of al theſe in acertain proportion mixid and temperid together, bi long digeſtion, and at length with a gentil diſtillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is creatid this caeleſtial oile, withoute adding or adioining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eniouther oile or liqeur whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as y can wel teſtifie hauing more then once ſeene the making thereof: Pondering then wel the reherſid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredience as y haue them faithfulli re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portid, he that wold aufft dout whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is were of a ſpecial efficacie, ſhold declare mutche his oune ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite
<pb facs="tcp:16101:14"/>and ignorance in the nature of things: For whereas thei be al and eache ſeueralli of notable greate uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, being here conioinid, vnitid, and commixid togeather, and then of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſo incorporatid, the foreſaid oile bi ſingular ingene, as the liffe, perfection, ſprite, quinteſſence and diuinar part, extract and drauuen fourth, it muſt neceſſarili comprehend in it ſelf the whole ſum of the particular vertues natural to al and eache ſuche ſimples: &amp; that in more perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; exact wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe then thei were before in the ſimples ſelf: nooutheruuiſe then Aqua uite skilfulli diſtillid, muche ſurpasſith the wine werefrom it is deſtillid, bothe in actiuite, ſimplicite, purite, penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſpeadi operation and diuers ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe.</p>
            <p>So that as experience witnesſith, theſame once deuidid from the wine, as the lif and ſoule there of, the reſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb facs="tcp:16101:14"/>in the bottome of the ſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, is as a boodi ſoules &amp; ſpriteles, hauing no taſt ne relleſs, but al vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie &amp; wateriſshe, therein reſting no moore propriete of wine: Euenſo the ſaide oile, as the veri hart blud &amp; ſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, of theſe reherſid ſimples, obtainith in it the effects, &amp; natural propretees of them al, in far more excellencie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the uery ſelf ſimples had them: And that becauſe there qualitees, ouermat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chid, hid &amp; allaid, with the groſs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial ſubſtance, and corpulencie, can not ſo cleareli declare there force, nor ſo exquiſiteli excerſice there diuine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, as being by art ſequeſtrate, diuidid, &amp; deliuerid of al materialnes. Neather here preuailith the cauillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſum, whiche mouid eather of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, or ignorancie, or els boothe, wold proue that neather this oile ne eni ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be ſo effectuous as the veri material compoſition of the ſimples
<pb facs="tcp:16101:15"/>from the whiche thei be extractid, bi the examples of diuers diſtillid wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: of whome ſum there herbs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bitter qualite, the water parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatith nothing of that taſt, but al bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternes lefft with the herbe, the water deſtillith rather ſuueete: Vuherebi it mai ſeame euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſuche water le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſing the apparent ſenſible qualitees, of the herb, shold alſo thereuuithal want the propreties due to ſuche qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litees: as is to be ſeene in the water of wurmwud, and the moſt part of al outher herbs.</p>
            <p>Hereto y anſuuere that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in waters, folouuith muche, throu the common vndiſcrete and raſshe diſtilling of them: whereas, were thei with more leaſar and ſofft tempering of the fire curiouſeli ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlid, thei shold retaigne by agreate deale better, the guſt &amp; taſt of there herbs, as diuers warie practiſars do know: But hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:16101:15"/>it cum to paſs in waters, in oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les is an nouthar reaſon: forſomuche as the oile of eueri thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is far more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſical and connatural to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof: Engendrid by a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; more exact labor &amp; induſtrie of nature, in tempering, mixing, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingling, &amp; circulating the materials or elements togeather with ſo mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and frindli action &amp; pasſion, the one within th'outher, thereto aiding the moderation of internal and exter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal heate as digeſtar, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>coctar, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par of al, that bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thus once, by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe meanes the contrariete &amp; ennimite of the foure Elements conciliate, and accordid togither, thei neuer affter bi eni meane can be ſeuerid a ſundar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: So ſtrait be thei enlinckid the one within the outher, that what vio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence ſo euer is done to them, eather go thei to geather, eatherels valientli remaigne togeather.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:16"/>
            <p>Oile then is the likeur moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent &amp; durable leſt ſubiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruption, diſſolution, disſipation: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein nature lockith &amp; vpcloſith al her iuels; In things animate, as man and outher liuing beaſts, it is the treaſor of there lift, wherewith there natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral heater, is fed, nouriſshid and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taignid: In plants and outher vegita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles it barith ſuche autorite, that whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it moſt Aboundith, there is that Plant moſt liueli, continuith longeſt, withſtandith beſt al iniuries of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, remaignith longar freſshe and greane: as the Baie tre, the Box, the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, the olife tre, the herbe Aloe, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie, and mani moo.</p>
            <p>Vuhereas outher being leſs oilie or gummi, hauing a moore fluy, and wateriſshe compoſition, ſoone fade, &amp; wither a waie, the weakenes of the water for eueri ſmal diſtemperancie of weather forſaking the ſubſtance
<pb facs="tcp:16101:16"/>wherein it was.</p>
            <p>Being then manifeſt, that the oili part of eache thing, is it, wherein the ſprites, life, and cheif vertue of theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me be conſeruid and moſt reſident; it is nothing tobe doutid but he whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che oute of eni plant can theſame ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feli withoute ouermuche violencie of fire extract, shal furth with enioie a liqeure muche more medicinable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al diſeaſes, then the plant ſelf: By reaſon that, beſides it hathe theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me qualitees, it hathe them in a moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſimplicite &amp; purite: Vuhat differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is betuuene qualitees annexid with tenuite, thinnes, or ſubtilite of ſubſtance, &amp; the ſame matchid with craſſenes of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vnto Phiſitions it is not vnknouen: Yet not al te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuite, thinnes, or ſubtilite of ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce wurkith with like efficacie in the bodie of man: Aqua vite, of whome we ſpake before, brought by offt rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration
<pb facs="tcp:16101:17"/>of diſtillation to ſuche extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſubtilie, that no waterie part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maign therein, ſo that aſponeful or ſauſarfull thereof bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſet a fire, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumith hooli in to flame, withoute le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing eni maner of humor or water behind: Thus handlid, y ſai, it is the moſt daintie, thin, fine, and ſimple li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qeur that by mans wit can be inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid: Not with ſtanding, eni vtter part of mans bodie being, for ſum cauſe bathid or fomentid thereuuith, ſkant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li it entre the poores of the skin, but veri ſwiftteli throu the ſmal hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the skin it ſmookith and drieth awai agein, leuing ſmal empresſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or efficacie behind it: Likeuuiſe againſt eni cold diſeaſe, or ſurfetts being drunck, what it cando, it doith ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denli &amp; oute of hand, warming the ſtomack, running euery where abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de into the vaines, multiplieng for a time &amp; conforting the debilitate ſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:16101:17"/>of the bodie: but ſuche his opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion right ſoone ceasſith &amp; his pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vaniſshith auuai anon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">the efficacie of oil Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</note>This preſent oile imperial being on eni external part e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nointid remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnith not without oppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the skin, ne by the heate thereof ſmokith or conſumith awaie, but ſpeadeliper cith, &amp; enterith the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, in maner without rubbing the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof on the skin: warming, opening, dilating theſame part, &amp; being the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reunder eni opilation, or collection of knotti cold humours, the ſame it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doith, diuidith, meltith, diſſoluith, and vtterli diſparſith: making waie, &amp; ſo preparing the matter, that nature, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in her eni force mai lightli dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge herſelf in expelling that, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che before throu groſſenes, withſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de al her poure &amp; endeuoure: Again, the ſame oile receauid by eni meanes within fourth, warmith the ſtomack,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:18"/>diſſoluith ventoſite, openith opilatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or ſtoppings engendrid of cold hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors; It pasſith alſo, albeit not ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteli as aqua uite, into the vaines, dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſelfe ueriuuhere; caried to the raigns or kidnees, prouokith urine breakith the, ſtoone: Mounting or deſcending, in the outher vaines of the boodie, for the oili part ſake it is the more familiarli receauid; throu qualitees annexid with ſubtilite &amp; extreame tenuite, diſsoluing and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieng cold and vndigeſtid humors ther found<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherebi thei be made the aptar, eather to be ouercum and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtid, orels utterli by ſwet, &amp; outher meanes of Expulſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be thruſt ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the boodi: Conuaied to the hart, it fortifieth and confortith the ſame, encreaſing the natural vigeur &amp; pour thereof: wherebi it mai the better withſtand the aſſalts, and inuaſions of eni uenemous or peſtelent uapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urs,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:18"/>by eni occations creaping the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reto.</p>
            <p>Theſe &amp; infinite outher effects it wurkith in the bodie of man, as ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuhat more particularli ſhalbe ſaide hereaffter, and that not ſlightli of paſsingli as aqua uite, whiche doith but as it were looke into the bodie, and ſodenli beſtoing it ſelf abroode, takith his leue again, not able throu the extreme ſimplicite of his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, to abide eni while the heate of the boodie, but of the ſame ueri ſoone is conſumid and reſoluid: but if it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauid with ale or wine it endurith longar in the bodi, and wurkith moore ſadli: The deades and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of oile Imperial be infiniteli more conſtant, &amp; ſtable: for bi reaſon of his oilines, it hathe his ſubſtance better compact, &amp; fixid to gither, and threrefore abidith, &amp; endurith lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar while, withſtanding the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines
<pb facs="tcp:16101:19"/>of the boodeli heate, fortifieng and encreaſing the ſame, becumming thereto an aide and ſoueraign ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kar, towards the vanqueſshing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, and ſubduing of eni noiſom and rebel humors; &amp; the retempering of eni diſtemperid part.</p>
            <p>And albeit that being, as it is, oile, and therefore ſum what of ſubſtance more craſſ, it mought ſeame, by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche, to be leſs apt with ſuche ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerite to be diſtributid into the vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as Aqua vite, whiche is, as it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nothing els but firi aier concretid into the ſimilitude of water; yet in this oile the foure elements, yea the groſſeſt of them, by the benefit of nature be ſo ſubtiliatid, raffinid, and depurid, that trueli neuer hitherto eni oile hathe ben, or, in mi opinion, by the wurke of nature ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, more ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſubtile and Aierial, Vvherebi veri ſpeadeli it exerſiſith his propreties, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16101:19"/>ſoone beſtouuith it ſelf abroode. Farther whereas Odor and gud ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, concurrant with good quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees is no ſmal commendation in eni maner of Medicine or meate appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to the vſe of mans boodie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſame the more grate, and Amiable vnto the receauar, &amp; ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieng ſum ſpecial grace of mixtion to the Medicine by celeſtial fauor &amp; influenceinſtinctid; no outher wiſe then in Muſick, certain concords &amp; conſonancies concurring together, engender aboue outher, a merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſuueatenes of armonie &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenli melodie, rauiſshing the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars in wunderful delight and reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: albeit that no man readili can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſufficient reaſon wherefore ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che concord more then outher, ſhold be agreable &amp; pleaſant to the eare of man: But whether the grace of gud ſauour, be to be aſcribid unto ſum
<pb facs="tcp:16101:20"/>particular and notable proportion &amp; conſonancie of the foure Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or els to ſum Quinteſſential propre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and diuine influxe, it wold breede a long proſſeſs to diſcuſs: Onli this of oile Imperial mai beaffirmid, that emong the oiles al, in good and uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous odor none mai be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parid to it: a plain teſtimoni that therein be hid and harberid ſprites of no ſmaul excellentie.</p>
            <p>So that whereas theſe mani yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res there hathe ben emong curious witts, greate contrauerſie and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, of the high medicine, namid for his excellent efficacie, in praeſeruing and prolonging the life of man, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xir vitae; althings indifferentli waied, and ſo comparid together, that laude and praeheminencie, mai muche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re iuſtli be attribute vnto this rare et wurthie oile, then vnto ſuche oiles, waters, Auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potabile, and outher
<pb facs="tcp:16101:20"/>fancies, by diuers alledgid, propoſid, and far aboue there merites exaltid and magnified: Notwithſtanding to auoid al fantaſtical vanite, y ſaie, the ueri true Elixir vitae, maintaignar and prorogar of the ſame, is the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom habite, ſtate, compoſiti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>on, or complexion of the boodi, upholden &amp; maintaignid with the temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of conuenient diete; eaquabilite of natural heate, ſtearid vp &amp; quickned throu neceſſarie and moderate exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice: And with excheuing the exces of al pasſions or affections of the mind: ln whome theſe propreties be founde, it mai be wel ſaid, the ſame to haue the veritrade, meane, and elixir of long and helthſum liff.</p>
            <p>But forſomuche as the blind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witchid wil of man, hath renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid the iuſt gouernance of reaſon, and yeldid it ſelf as captif to the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical iuriſdiction of vnbridlid ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual
<pb facs="tcp:16101:21"/>and appetites, it folowith, that feu or none there be, al thouh there ſtate or complexions be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralli neuerſo firmed &amp; good, but that throu execsſiue miſuſe of bodili ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and appetites, it is alterid, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertid, and corruptid: The natural heate, gouernar, framer, deuiſar, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and cauſe general of al opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the bodie, eather by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluite oppresſid, ſcarcite deminiſshid or euel qualite into diſtemperancie alterid: Vuereas then, al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort ſtrength, motion, ſenſe, al the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; actions of the boodie (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſidesfurth with his apt and due membres or inſtruments furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſshid) conſiſtith &amp; dependith chiefeli oppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſafe and temperate main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the natural heate inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did vniuerſalli in al &amp; eueri part of the bodi; by whoſe preſence eache part is hablid to attract his conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
<pb facs="tcp:16101:21"/>nutriment, &amp; the ſame to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt &amp; aſſemble to it ſelf, the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitees not agreable or neceſſari to refuce, and by conuenient meanes to expel; by whoſe moderation alſo, the vapors or ſprites of life, of ſenſe, of motion, be engendrid conſeruid &amp; made apt to Animate &amp; ſteere vp the inſtruments of the boodie, eache to the execution of his deputid office: yff it hap therefore, that the ſame ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ouer, or vnder, in quantite or qualite, becum oppresſid, or decaid, that medicine whiche beſt, withmoſt expedition, &amp; ſecurite, can help to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoore, repaire, and ſet on foote again the lapſe or fal of the ſaid natural heate, aiding and coadiuting it to the uanqueſſhing and repulſing of al ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſrie cauſes, ſuche Medicine mai, and that not vnwurtheli be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid an Elixir, or prorogar of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in life.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:22"/>
            <p>This oure Oile, iuſtli callid impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, in this caſe is ſo mighti and ua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, in helping and Farthering na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heare, to the clearing &amp; vnſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of al obſtructions and ſtuffing of eni part in the bodie, in rarifieng the denſite or clooſenes engendrid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni where, by what occation ſo euer it be, in encreaſing heate decaid, that his operation ſurmountith al praiſe and commendation: and therefore mai wurtheli be holden and eſtemid for The verie Elixir of liff: The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che when ye when ye be diſpoſid to vſe aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt eni diſeaſe,<note place="margin">Oile Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial mai be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amid the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ixir of life.</note> eather withinfurth, or withoutefurth, not mindid to vſe the ſame alone, if ye mix it with ſum outher ſuche ſimples or compoſts as be aggreable to that diſeaſe, infiniteli ſhal the uertue of that ſimples or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts, by the preſence of this oile, be enhaunſid &amp; encreaſid, with muche moore ſpeade and efficacie perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:16101:22"/>there lookidfor effects.</p>
            <p>And to thend that with the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluite of mani woords the readar, be not faſtidiat &amp; ouer cloied, or there deſire to be reſoluid of the final and uttar vertues of the ſaid offt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nid oile, eni longar holden in ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, y wil hereaffter brieffli, and as it were with mi fingar ſuperficialli po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>int vnto certain particular diſeaſes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whiche y, and outher, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue offte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it ſingularli ſouueraign: not partialli deſcribi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g eueri ſmal cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance to be vſid therein: for that wold becu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matter of a greatar uolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: and beſides that argue in me a ſuperſtiſious arrogancie, in that it mought ſeme y had ſo ſlendar an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of outher mens iudgements, to thinck that vnleeſe y declarid peeſe by peeſe eueri particle, thei ſhold be to ſeeke, hou to there pourpoſes at eni time to applie the ſame: Iknou tho
<pb facs="tcp:16101:23"/>y ſhold minſe the matter neuer ſo ſmal, or enlarge it ſo muche as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught be, yet feu bether that without the aduiſe of ſum diſcreate and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nid phiſition, wold in eni Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant diſeaſe entremedle therewith: Not that this Oile of it ſelf, is litil or moore dangerous, but for this reaſon that the moſt innocent medicine in the wordle, yea oure familiar meate, &amp; drinck, vſid oute of conuenient ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or where it were better forbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, or affter ſum vnordinate ſort, mai and daili do, brede diſpleaſirs:</p>
            <p>To the expert then, that whiche before y haue al readie in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaid, is ſufficient: Not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for there ſake whiche haue not that diſcourſe nor exact iudgement of the ſequele and conſequencie of things, y wila litil broodar extend mi tale, and ſpecifie a certain of the moſt notable diſeaſes whereto this
<pb facs="tcp:16101:23"/>oile is found effectuous: Firſst begin at the hed as capitain general &amp; ouerſear of al the reſt of the boodi.</p>
            <p>In the hed of man,<note place="margin">diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hed.</note> from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp; the cauls of the brain, al the Synues of the bodi he engendrid, &amp; frome thenſe by certain meanes, diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied and ſent furth vnto al outher parts of the bodi; Throu the whiche Sinue, oute of the ſaid braines, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal and fontain, be diſtribute and diſparſid the ſpirits and vapours of ſenſe and Mouing: without whoſe preſence, no membre nor por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bodi can once eather moue or feele; ſo that whereas the mouth and hed ſpring of the ſynues is in the hed, and the ſprites opon the ſubtilar part of the blud engendrid do make there, ther firſt entrance in to the foreſaid ſynues, throu there ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacite caried eueri els where: it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penith ſumtime that, groſs, and uiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous
<pb facs="tcp:16101:24"/>ſuperfluous humours, engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid, and amasſid or heapid in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, or ſum peſtele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and venemous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified humor aſſending fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior part to the topkaſtel of the hed do obſtruct or ſtopp, more or leſſe, the ſaid gates, ports &amp; entries of the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: Vuhereby doith enſue, that the ſprits being prohibitid there accuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid courſe, the ſenſe of fealing &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bodi, the one alone, or the outher, or bo the for a time is dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſshid or decaied.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">he Apople<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</note>If the Opilation &amp; ſtopping be vttar and exact, cumming of cold craſſ humors, it engendrith the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſeaſe callid the Apoplexia: wherein al bodili ſenſe and motion be ſo brought a ſleepe, and failid, that offt times the patient, xxiiii. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res or more, lieth ſo ſenſeles that it appearith the ſame of at liffe to be wholi deſtitute.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:24"/>
            <p>The falling ſicknes alſo procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith like cauſes;<note place="margin">the falling ſicknes.</note> but the oppilation cauſing that diſeaſe is not ſo exact &amp; extreme; wherefore thei that fal, be not vtterli priuate of ſenſe &amp; motion: For we ſee them beating there heds and bodi; And that beating of there hed, no dout is done by the inſtinct of nature: By reaſon that whereas the paſſage of the ſprites of Motion, is not quite ſtopt vp, but onli that by the acceſſe of ſuche corrupt humor, there courſe is interruptid, and thei therebi, as it were ſtranglid, nature whiche alwais is induſtrious to ſaue herſelf in her due being, mouith the patient to beſtere himſelf: but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialli to ſteer the part offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did or gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auid; therebi the better &amp; ſonar to deliuer it ſelf from encoumbrance of the wickid humor occatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuche diſturbance: as the like maner ſhe vſith in vometing: at what time
<pb facs="tcp:16101:25"/>naturalli the ſtomack is prouokid to diſcharge it ſelf from noiſum hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors occupieng that place: And alſo in the cough the weaſand being tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>klid, or irritate bi ſum humors deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereto, whiche, were not the preſent reſiſtence of that place, wold forcebli entre in to the windpipe, to the paril of ſtrangling the partie.</p>
            <p>Item in the Hed happenith an ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tedious diſeaſe callid the Paulſy. Vuhiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>li, proceadith of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not unlike the foreſaid: houbeit not ſo vehement ne dangerous. And moſt times enſuith rather of diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantie and debilite of the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of mouing, whiche be the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, then of eni aboundance, or euil qualite or quantite of humors oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the mouthes of the ſaide ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</p>
            <p>Farther,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng</note> in the Hed do raign the diſeaſes callid, Caros .i. the ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb facs="tcp:16101:25"/>ſicknes: And Vertigo, that is, the Turnſicknes, or ſwiming of the hed: with Catalepſis, whihe ſignifieth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tounnidnes, or Amaſidnes: with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers outher: Al whiche, with the reſt what ſoeuer thei be, haue ſum time there cauſes onli in the hed, and ſum times, or rather moſt, take ther origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of the ſtomack.</p>
            <p>For, the ſtomack in compariſon of the hed, mai be reſemblid to the pan or bottome of a ſtillatorie; and the Hed, to the deck or lembick of the ſtillatori: ſo that, what ſoeuer humors or outher matter is found in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, theſame throu the natural he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate of that place reſoluid in to reekes, fumes, or vapors, and the ſaide vapors ſtieng from thens and breathing up in the hed, as thei be affectid &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſid in them ſelf, ſo do thei affect &amp; diſpoſe the hed &amp; his parts: If then ſuche vapors be ſtincking, corrupt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilſauorid,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:26"/>reſoluid from ſum putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied &amp; rotton humors, thereopo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be engendrid in the Hed, other the Turnſicknes, the Palſie, the falling ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cknes, or els ſum outher notable grief: as Apoſtumations in ſundrie regions of the hed: whiche when thei be ripid and broken, ſend furth the matter by the eares, or the nooſe, or the roofe of the mouthe, or eyes, or outhewiſe as nature findith moſt accommodate place &amp; region to thruſt furth ſuche matter: offt times alſo it engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drith ſtincking and rotten teathe and bretthe, with diſcoulorid eyes, &amp; duſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kid eye ſight: as alſo trooblid wittes &amp; euil memori.</p>
            <p>Againſt al theſe inconueniens; oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le imperial takin inward, beit alone or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioignid with outher co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenable things (as anon ſhalbe ſaide) ſhouith exceding efficacie: throu his holſome &amp; aromatical odor, with correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:16101:26"/>qualities, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forting the ſtomack, drie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp, and ſincering alputrifactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the uertue whereof mounting into the hed, there cuttith, deuidith, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparſith al craſsnes &amp; tenacite of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, attenuating matters congeilid &amp; cludderid together: opening al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilations, chieff cauſars of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, palſie, falling ſicknes, ſleapi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes, Aſtunnidnes, ſwiming, rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, ſinging, &amp; piping in the eares; diſpatchith old aches be thei i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repart or hinder part of the hed, or ells in the ſides of the hed, callid Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gremes: it makith the brethe ſwete: it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmith the Memoratiue part, dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid by reaſon of cold, or outherwiſe euil diſpoſid humors: It fortifieth the vigeur and pour of the ſynues: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſith alſo the liuelines &amp; agilite of the ſprites bothe of motion &amp; ſenſe: clarifieth the eyeſight, quickenith the ſenſe of odor or ſauour: and likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:16101:27"/>the ſenſe of hearing: Stearith vp the viuacite and preſent readines of wit and comprehention or vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">a pretious me dicine made uuith oile im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial.</note>The vſe of the ſaide oile in theſe caſes, accompanied with outher ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hauing reſpect to ſuche diſeaſes, as y haue offt vſid, is in this wiſe: Take of the floures of roſemarie, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, betoni, yſope, Gelifloures, primro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Couſlips, damaſk roſes, of eache of theſe floures the waight of .vi. pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: of the freſshiſt leaues of Mariorame, of winter ſauerie, Terragon, penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, and ſwete garden Mints: of eache the waight of .iiii. pens: of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Peoni, of Baſil, of ſwete Fenil, of Aniſe, of eache the waight of .iiii. pens: of fine Cinamome, nutmeggs, &amp; Mace, of eache the waigth of .v. pens: And whereas al the foreſaid floures can not be had at one ſeaſon: let eache in his ſeaſon be gatherid, &amp; that in a
<pb facs="tcp:16101:27"/>faire drie morning, affter the ſun haue one half or one hole houre, ſhone thereopon: then on a faire linen clot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the lai them abrode in the aier, oute of the ſun to drie alitil, the ſpace of vi. or .viii. houres: whiche done, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the foremencionid waight of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and thre times as muche white ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt to pouder: and in a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne mortar beate the floures and ſugre together til thei be wel te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perid th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne with the outher, conſerue wiſe: the whiche ye ſhal reſerue in ſum broode mouthid glaſs or galli ſtone pott, vntil ye haue al your flours in readines: And as hathe ben ſaide of the flours, ſo do likewiſe with the herbs in eueri point: As for the ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drie droges, ye ſhal beate them in to pouder, and after, in a ſtone mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar with the conſerue of the flours, &amp; herbs, ſtamp them and mixt them perfetli in one, adding thereto, drop
<pb facs="tcp:16101:28"/>after drop, the quantite of .ii. ſpone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of oile Imperial, continualli ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſtamping, til al be wel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate together: This precious Electuarie, not alone againſt the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue reherſid diſeaſes, but alſo, al outher inward diſeaſes is moſt mighti and preſent remedi: And as the diſeaſe is greater or leſſar, ſo is it to be vſid in more or leſſ quantite, and offtnar or ſeldomar times: Being the diſeaſe greate, it is to be taken two times the daie: that is .iii. houres before diner, and .ii. hours or more affter ſuppar, at eache time the quantite or waight of ii. grootes: eather alone, or els with ſum deſtillid water, or ſum gud thin brotth; or if the partie be of comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion veri cold, with ſum malueſie, or romeni, or outher gud white wine: thus continuing the ſpace of fortie daies: Preſuppoſing that if the quanti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te or qualite of the humors cauſars of
<pb facs="tcp:16101:28"/>ſuche diſeaſe, do require it, that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me by the aduiſe of ſum expert Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhold be purgid &amp; clenſid, to thend the medicine mai the better &amp; with more ſucceſſ wurk: not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to vſe therewithal, conformable &amp; accommodate diete.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">hou oile im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial is to be taken alone.</note>But who that liſtith to receaue it withoute being accompagnied with ſuche, or outher conſerues, ſhal find it nothing the leſſ vertuous in his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; at what time it is to be taken at the foreſaid preſcript ſeaſons, one quartar of a ſponeful at once, with iiii. or .v. ſponeſulls of Muſcatel, or outher ſwete wine, otherels with as muche of the brotthe of mutton, vele, or chicken: Sum dipp therein a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of bred, &amp; ſo eate it: ſupping affter it, a dooſen ſponefulls of thin brotthe: Outher take it with figgs, or with a li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>til clarified honi, or fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyrupe, ſugre, or eni co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue: as the conſerue of rooſes,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:29"/>of borage, Bugloſs, roſemarie, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che like: there be alſo that rolling the pouder of liqueriſe in this oile, make thereof pills, the whiche thei ſwallou whole: eueri man as his ſtomack can ſerue him beſt: Not that the oile of it ſelf is lotheſum or tedious to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauid, but forbecauſe therebe mani of ſo tender ſtomacks, that the ſame wil admit nothing miniſtrid in the name of a medicine, vnleſs it be coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid with ſum outher more familiar thing: Houſoeuer ye deale with it, ſo it be conuaied in to the bodi it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kith no greate matter: and that ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membar to encreaſe or diminiſshe, the quantite of it, proportionalli to the vehementie, or ſlacknes of the diſeaſe: As that the ſmalliſt quantite be .v. or .vi. drops: The greatiſt half a ſponeful at once, not that in exceding the ſaid meaſure there were eni peril, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame mai ſeame ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:16101:29"/>for one time againſt eni neuer ſo ſtrong &amp; rebel diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Thus whether it be miniſtrid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, otherels, according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreation of the phiſition, matchid with outher agreable medicines, it bringith furth ſuche effect, as of eni wurthie medicine mai be lookidfor: And that not alone in cold diſeaſes but alſo in the hott: For, whereas co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>li there is no hot diſeaſe but that it is engendrid by incluſion &amp; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning of ſum humors, be thei hot or cold, in al the vaines, or in ſum cornar of the vains, bouwels, orou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intrailes, or eni fleſshie or muſkli part of the bodi: where being coartid, pent, &amp; ſtraightnid, thei putrifie ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulder, and kendel an vnnatural fire or heate, yea tho the humor before ſuche incluſion were neuer ſo cold, no outherwiſe then wette Hey or Strau, laid in a cloſe houſe withoute
<pb facs="tcp:16101:30"/>vent, &amp; the ſaid putrified humors as thei putrifie more and more, ſo wex thei hotter and hottar, by whiche heate again thei reſolue in to ſuche reekes &amp; fumes, that the place whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein thei be in ſtoppid and lodgid, becumming to ſtraight for them, thei ſtriue, and contend to getfurth: but if al yſſue be dinied them, then ſuche ſtriffe, and contention, turnid into ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and furie, fillith the pour patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ofttimes ſo ful of intollerable anguiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>she &amp; dolor, that deathe were to be preferrid.</p>
            <p>Therfore that, whiche can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtop, &amp; ſet at large ſuche humors, by conſequent curith the diſeaſe thereo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enſuid: for ſuche furious firy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, being once enlargid, and ſet at there libertie, ſoone diſpatche, diſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and conſume the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf: thereto hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the expulſiue pour of nature (if ſhe haue not bene to muche alreadi
<pb facs="tcp:16101:30"/>oppresſid) inſet in eueri membre, and part of the boodi, to repel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf things noiſum: For this reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al Intermitting agues, as the Quotidian, the Tertia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">against al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</note> and the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agues, this Imperial oile is muche excellent: becauſe that the ſeueral hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, cauſes original of theſe foreſaid Agues, throu putrefaction chaungid &amp; alterid from there natural ſtate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maign pen tup and inclooſid in ſum ſpetial place, where thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them ſelf, ne eaſeli get furth. Vuerefore to vnſtop &amp; enlarge al ſuche opilations, one houre before ye ſuſpect the ague ſhal inuade the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, geue him to drinck one quartar of a ſponeſul of oile imperial, with xii. or .xv. ſponefulls of poſſet ale, or wine, or ſum outher good thin brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, forthwith doing what mai be done, to prouoke the partie to ſwet before the fit of the Ague do entre:
<pb facs="tcp:16101:31"/>Iff ye liſt to vſe the Electuari, whereof we wrote before, ye mai as wel: but in caſe, beſides the ſaid drinck, ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint all the ridge of the patients back, from the raigns vp wards vnto betwene the ſhulders, with the oile of Camomel temperid with a litil of this ſoueraign oile, the better ſhal the ague be preuentid, and the ſonar ſhal the patient ſwet: This ordar being kept .ii. or .iii. times, before the aſſault of the fitt, no doute al the occation of ſuche Ague, wilbe diſchargid: onleſs beſidesfurth there be to greate diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar in diete.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">againſt the pestilence.</note>To preſerue eni man from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the peſtilence, if he take ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che daie, or eache outher dai, in the morning faſting, of the aboue writin Electuari, or of this oile alone, one ſmal quartar of a ſponeful, with ſum ſuche things as be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brid before, it ſhalbe found ſingular in preſeruing:
<pb facs="tcp:16101:31"/>But if eni be alreadi ſeaſoni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with the plage, then twiſe the dai, morning and euening, with a quantite of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lei water, or ſum outher thin brotthe or rather with the mountnance of a walnut of gud Thriacle, or Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum, geue the infectid half a ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neful of this oile, incontinentli pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking him to ſwet: and diet him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidesfurth, as appartainith:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">against poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; ueno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</note>Alſo againſt poiſons, ſtingings, or bitings of eni venemous beaſts or mad doggs, the ſaid oile taken as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with Mithridatum, or theriacle withſtandith the venemoſnes of ſuche ſting or bite, from approching neere or inuading the hart or eni ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther principal part: Is likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to be ennointid oppon the place ſtung or bitt; or to be temperid with Emplaſtars vſualli made for ſuche purpoſes, wherebi there vertue retractiue ſhalbe made dooble: Beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
<pb facs="tcp:16101:32"/>that the ſubtilite of the oile ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuche wund wil alter and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſshe the malice of the venime, that tho it do penetrate farther in thebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, yet accompanied and matchid wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the ſaide oile, it ſhal haue no pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to do eni viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci to the parts whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it ſhal paſs by.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">for the ſuuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>For them that are muche diſpoſid to poue, or ſwound, if, affter eni ſort thei liſt, it be efftſones vſid, it ſhal deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them of that Infirmite: to them that be ſwounid or faintid .v. or .vi. dropps thereof withe a ſponeful of white wine or Muſkatel pourid in to there mouth, there temples alſo, &amp; ther noſeſtrels rubbid therewith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuith &amp; callith them again to them ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">against diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the ſplene.</note>Therebe whoſe Splene or Melt, is ſo obſtruct and ſtopt with groſs Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cholious humors, that neather, according to the due office of that
<pb facs="tcp:16101:32"/>bouwel, it can by attracting the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholi part, deliuer the blud ther of: neather yet expurge it ſelf from that it hathe alreadi conceauid, the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bothe of entrance, and yſſue being obſtruct and ſtoptup. Vuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi enſuith diuers greuous diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the bodi: for whereas the Melancholy humor, is the droſſ, dreggs, &amp; as it weere the lies, &amp; terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial part of the blud; remaining vndiuidid &amp; vnſequeſtratid from the purar part of the ſame, it farith furth, &amp; pasſith eueriwhere, with the blud, troobling, darckning, obſcuring the clarite and brightnes thereof: as the purite, and clearenes of wine is defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid, and diſcolorid, and the good rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thereof deſtroied, when the lies hanging in the ſubſtance of it, troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſame: nether can be by ſum ſlyght, depurid therefro, and the lies to his place, the bottome, returnid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gein:
<pb facs="tcp:16101:33"/>Thei in whome the blud affter this ſort is with ſuche felouſhip in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectid, be inclinid muche to al Heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, penſifnes, withoute eni external cauſe: thei feale the light of there witts and ſprites, obfuſkat, &amp; darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nid: thei abhor and hate compani, deſirous of ſolitarines; be ful of diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ire, weepe, murne, by them ſelf cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: be muche ſuſpitious, ſoone take vnkindnes and diſpleaſirs, reioice in nothing, and weri of this lif, oft deſire deathe: al theſe, with mani mo tedius pasſions, folou &amp; moleſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe blud is aſſoſiatid, withe that ſad, &amp; black humor the Melancholi: But to greatar danger, and perillous paine be thei ſubiectid, whoſe Melt, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ben ſaid being obſtructid, the black humor that therein reſtith, at certain ſeaſons ſwellith, puffith, &amp; heauith up, like ſoure leuen or barme, in do we: or as vineger, or ſtrong wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:16101:33"/>falling on the earth, his ſith &amp; lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith vp it ſelf in bubbles or bladders: throu the whiche ſwelling and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the bowel of the Splene, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein ſuche ſoure Melancholi humor is comprehendid, is bi that occation diſtendid, and pufft vp, more then his natural: and therefore requirith more roome or place then he was wunt, to the iniurie and oppresſion of his neighbars: as pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipalli the Stomack &amp; the Midriff: whereopon offtimes during the time of ſuche inflation, if it be vehement, the patient leaſith his ſpeche: becauſe the Midriff is ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nid or interruptid of his due ſcope, or wunt courſe: and the ſtomack na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meli the mouthe or entrie thereof, moleſtid and ſtraighnid bi the ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſplene, whiche lieth in maner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thwart the ſtomack: For, theſe parts be as chief, in enlarging or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholding the ſpeeche: as in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack
<pb facs="tcp:16101:34"/>mai be ſeen by daili experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: if a man ſwollou a peſe of meete, breade, or outher thing, whiche not ſtrait enterith in to the capacite of the ſtomack: but reſtith and ſtaieth at the mouth of the ſtomack ſo long as the ſame there remainith, the partie in no wiſe ſhalbe hable to ſpeake one wurd: and that for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cauſes nedeles in this place to be reherſid.</p>
            <p>The ſaid ſplenetic patients, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone faile of there ſpeache, but allſo manitimes haue there mouthes drau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen on the one ſide, there eyes ſtaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, a continual aſſai, and endeuer, to ſpeeke, if it wold be; with veri painful retraction of the ſinues; ſo that mani times i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mediateli enſuith deathe with muche anguiſshe, to the greate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pasſion of the beholdars: Againſt al theſe incommodities, whether it be with inflation of the ſplene, or onli a
<pb facs="tcp:16101:34"/>continual hardnes, and ſwelling the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, nothing can be excogitate more preſent reamedi, then the daili vſe of this Oile affter ſuche ſort as hathe be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before preſcribid: togither with offt ennointing of the lefft ſide vnder the ſmal ribbs, with this effectuous oile: and by mixtion thereof, witheni ſuche ointment or plaſtar as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſid to that pourpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">against the collick or ſtitches.</note>There be feu, that at one time or outher haue not felt the biſie dolor of the collick; or the sharp ſtabbs and ſtitches in the breſt, ſides, or outher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, diſtending, ſtretching, &amp; as it were racking, tearing, &amp; pulling a ſundre the gutts, the breſt, or outher part where eni ventoſite is ſo encloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrid &amp; pent, in that in no wiſe it can get furth: This Oile then, receauid bi the mouthe affter eni ſort it pleaſith the patient, or the phiſition to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre it: conuaied alſo with a gliſtar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:16101:35"/>the gutts, or if neade be ennointid on the belli, the ſide, the breſt, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, or eni outher place wher ſuche ventoſite is engendrid &amp; includid, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtili diſſoluith, diſparſith, and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſshith the ſame, and that in ſmal time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">for the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite of the ſtomack.</note>So that mani being encombrid with crudite, or raunes of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, and by conſequence with ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſite, offt belchings, &amp; curling, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or rumbling in the gutts, by vſing once the daie or once in .ii. da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies, half an houre before diner .iii. or iiii. drops of this oile, more or leſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cauſe, haue recouuerid good digeſtion with concoction of al crudite.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Against the ſtone.</note>For the ſtone, be it in the Rains or in the bladdar, being receauid alone or temperid with outher conuenient things, and the rains withoutefurth ennointid therewith alone, or alaid
<pb facs="tcp:16101:35"/>with the oile of rooſes, or bittar al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to the phiſitions diſcreation: li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewiſe if the ſtone be in the bladdar, thereof conuaied into the bladdar, &amp; the neck of the bladdar, or the ſhaare with it curiouſli enointid, it penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith, &amp; by penetration breakith, pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derith, and crummith the ſtone, in ſuche wiſe that no outher medicine can be found of the like ſpeadi effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towards that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">for the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſicknes.</note>Againſt the grene ſicknes in we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the ſtopping or ſtaieng of ther natural courſe, as alſo to diſpoſe them the better to conception, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be druncken, or with conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient meanes (as weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do knou) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaied to the priui places, it hath ben found alwais a thing of greate aad readi ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Againſt impotentie to the wurks of generation, bothe in man and woman, proceading eather by infri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidation
<pb facs="tcp:16101:36"/>of the parts generatif, or ſum obſtruction, withſtanding the due courſe of the ſprites &amp; vapors, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſteerers to that act, this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial oile, therewith offt times being enointid the parts generatifs, is ueri ſingular.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Againſt the flux of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note>Take of Maſtick, of the floures of Pome granate, of Mirtil beries, of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the half an ounce: beate them to pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and temper them withe .vi. ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefulls of this Oile, incloſing al to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in a litil vial of glaſs, ſetting it a ſunning, ten or twelue dais; with this oile ennoint the neck of the bladdar, whiche lieth betwene the foundment and the yard, with alſo bothe the genitories, eueri dai twiſe &amp; therebi shall ſeaſe, be ſtaid &amp; ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, the continual flux of nature, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith mani be muche greauid &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feobliſshid.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">for the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh.</note>Againſt the cough, and whiſing
<pb facs="tcp:16101:36"/>or whiſtling of the throote, for short bretthe, &amp; al maner of ſtopping or ſtuffing in the Lungs, take this oile with ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Syrupe of liqueriſe, of Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denheere, or hyſſope: or mix it with ſwete buttar and ſugre, and ſo vſing it, it shal cleare and vnſtop the lungs meruelouſeli.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">for the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ake.</note>For the touthe ake, the gums the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith rubbid, or in caſe the touthe be hollou .iii. or .iiii. drops thereof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaied into the holones of the touthe, ſwagith ſwifftli the anguiſshe and dolor thereof: and if there be eni pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therein, theſame drieth &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerith it.</p>
            <p>Againſt the ſwelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g abought the throote callid the kings euil,<note place="margin">the kings e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil.</note> theſame being two times the dai enointid wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th this oile alone, or ells mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>glid with ſum outher weakar oiles, with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce by litil &amp; litil, reſoluith and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith quite awai.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16101:37"/>
            <p>The whole hed therewith, nou et then enointid, preſeruith the heere fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling, and conſeruith them in there naturall coulor, withſtanding bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and hoorenes, cauſith the here, in the hed or berd to proſpar and grou long; the whole hed likewiſe enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intid, and thereof conuaid into the noſtrells, purgith the hed, openith the ſenſe of ſmelling, and wurckith ſtoutli againſt the Apoplex, the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and ſuche outher diſeaſes of the hed .ii. or .iii. drops pourid in to the eare, clearith, the ſenſe of hering, and breakith apoſtumations in the hed if eni ſuche be; the two temples, and the noddel of the hed, once in a wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ennointid with it, cauſith good &amp; freſshe memori.</p>
            <p>Againſt the ſciatica, whiche is a greate paine in the hipp: againſt all old and neu aches, in the shulders, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, ioints, leggs, feete; old bruſes, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="tcp:16101:37"/>within &amp; withoutfurth; againſt the Morpheu, the leprie, ſerpigo, ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlegm in the face, with mani outher infections of the skin: Againſt old ſoors, Fiſtulas, the ſtincking exulcerations of the frenche pocks, with an infinite number of outher Infirmities, to long here to be reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid, it is ſo excellent, that to declare them one by one, and to shou the particular vſe of this gracious oile with al circumſtances, were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to occupie a greate volume: Vuherefore to auoide farther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixite, with this ſmal declaration, the gentil readars for this time shal hold them contentid: leauing the reſt to the iudgement of the diſcreate &amp; ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nid in Phiſicck.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
